Guide to the Beat poets and poetry collection,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Beat poets and poetry collection,
1959-1971.
0.5 linear ft. (1 half-sized document box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#0091
4079081
A collection of manuscripts and correspondence of beat poets and others affiliated with the Beat Generation.
Scope and Content
This is an artificial collection of correspondence and manuscripts by members of the beat generation assembled by curators and staff of the Rare Book & Manuscript Library. The collection includes manuscripts by writers such as LeRoi Jones, Claude Pelieu, and Thomas McGrath as well as pieces of correspondence written by Neal Cassady (to Ken Kesey) and Gary Snyder.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 1 series: Series 1: Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1959-1971.
Subjects
Brakhage, Stan.; Cassady, Neal.; Clark, Tom.; Baraka, Imamu Amiri, 1934-; Lebel, Jean Jacques.; McGrath, Thomas, 1916-1990.; Murphy, Anne.; Pélieu, Claude.; Ray, David.; Snyder, Gary.; Beat generation.; Poets.; Poetry, Modern--20th century.; Bohemianism.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
M59
- Series 1: Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1959-1971
  This series, which comprises the entirety of the collection, contains correspondence and manuscripts related to beat writers and the cultural movement known as the Beat Generation.
  - Brakhage, Stan to David Gitlin, 1968 August (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cassady, Neal to Ken Kesey, 1965 August-September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clark, Tom to David Gitin, 1968 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Farrell, Barry to Charles Plymell, undated (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fine, Albert to Claude Pelieu, 1969-1971, (3 postcard collages) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Gwerder, Urban to Claude Pelieu, 1969 June, (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Jim" to David Gitin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jones, LeRoi (Amiri Baraka)- The Systems of Dante's Hell manuscript fragment with corrections, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lebel, Jean Jacques to Claude Pelieu, undated and 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    (3 postcards- one to Pelieu and Lawrence Ferlinghetti)
  - McGrath, Thomas Poetry Manuscripts
    - "Giuffre's Sheepherder" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Long Distance" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Life in the Peasant Department" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Sound of One Hand" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "O'Leary's Last Wish" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Sound of One Hand" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Song" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "A Field of Sunflowers" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Sound of One Hand" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Presumptions" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Too Bad" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Sound of One Hand" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "War Resisters Song" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Sound of One Hand" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Where Janie Went In" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Arrivals" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - McGrath, Thomas to Ron Wolin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Murphy, Anne to Neal Cassady, 1965 August (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Claude Pelieu
    - to Albert Fine, 1969 April 7, (2 postcards) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Collages (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Poetry Manuscripts- "Airplane Poem" and "Coeur d'Alene," undated and 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Plymell, Charles- 3 items relating to Charles Plymell (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ray, David to Charles Plymell, circa 1968 (3 letters) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Snyder, Gary to Jack Hirschmann, 1959 April-May, (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 18)